## Vikram Voleti

PhD candidate at Mila; former Research Intern at Google, Unity, Meta; 4+ years of work experience

woletiv.github.io wikram.voleti@gmail.com
Google Scholar
In LinkedIn

EXPERTISE

Deep learning for image, video, 3D: expert at machine learning research and development; experienced in leading multiple projects collaborating with international partners in industry and academia.

Projects include: • Score-based denoising diffusion models for video [1], deriving non-isotropic covariance [2]

- Image generation using normalizing flows [4][9]; video generation using Neural ODEs [13], GANs [15][16]
- 3D human pose estimation and inverse kinematics [3], 3D object generation using NeRFs, diffusion
- Contributed to projects on 4D generation, simulation [10], fairness/uncertainty [5], federated learning [6]

EDUCATION

## Mila, University of Montreal, Canada

Sep 2018 - present (Aug 2023)

Ph.D. in Computer Science — Supervisor: Prof. Christopher Pal

Tindian Institute of Technology (IIT), Kharagpur, India

2009 - 2014

Dual Degree (B.Tech. (Honours) + M.Tech.) in Electrical Engineering with Master's specialization in Instrumentation and Signal Processing

RESEARCH INTERNSHIPS DURING PHD Meta (formerly Facebook), Menlo Park, USA

Aug-Dec 2022

 $\it Team:$  AI for Metaverse (AI4RL);  $\it Supervisors:$  Dr. Yashar Mehdad, Dr. Barlas Oguz

- ullet Research and development of solutions for text to 3D object generation using diffusion models, NeRF
- Led project in collaboration with international teams, applied research to virtual reality product

**William Technologies**, Montreal, Canada (MITACS Research Intern)

Oct 2021 - Aug 2022

Team: Deep Pose, Unity Labs; Supervisor: Dr. Boris Oreshkin

- 3D human pose estimation and inverse kinematics from videos, published at SIGGRAPH Asia [3]
- Led project on AI-assisted animation workflows, contributed to product pipeline with code, demos
- Google, Mountain View, USA

Sep-Dec 2019

Team: Google AI Perception; Supervisors: Dr. Bryan Seybold, Dr. Sourish Chaudhuri

• Research on multimodal semi-supervised Active Speaker Detection in videos

Work

IIIT Hyderabad, India — Research Fellow; Supervisor: Prof. C. V. Jawahar

May 2017 - Aug 2018

EXPERIENCE

- Synthesized educational videos in regional Indian languages by generating lips from audio
- Developed automated pipeline to create large-scale audio-video dataset
- Full paper published at ICASSP 2019 [15], short paper published at CVPR 2018 Workshop [16]

 ${\bf GreyOrange~Robotics}, \, {\bf Gurgaon}, \, {\bf India} - {\bf Image~Processing~Engineer}$ 

Feb 2016 - May 2017

- ullet Developed computer vision solutions for embedded robotics in real time for warehouse automation
- Solely responsible for code development and testing of video processing module, camera drivers, server

Airbus, Bengaluru, India — Associate Engineer

Jul 2014 - Feb 2016

• Avionics software development following standard avionics coding guidelines (DO-178B)

PROFESSIONAL

OTHER

Blue Lion Labs, Canada — AI Advisor

Oct 2020 - present

EXPERIENCE

Provide technical guidance and mentorship on the design and development of AI/ML systems
Mentor co-op students and interns, published research papers from work led by them [6][8]

TE Wientor co-op students and interns, published research papers from work led by them [0][0]

 $\mathbf{NextAI},$  Canada — AI Scientist-in-Residence

Apr-Sep 2019, Mar-Sep 2020

• Provided scientific and technical support to start-ups selected in yearly co-hort of NextAI accelerator

Playment, Bengaluru, India — Computer Vision Consultant

Jan-Jun 2018

• Provided technical guidance on semantic segmentation models for autonomous driving

TalentSprint, Hyderabad, India — Mentor, Foundations of AI & ML (inaugural program) Jan-May 2018

Designed and delivered tutorials on machine learning, and provided mentorship to industry professionals

Awards

Outstanding Reviewer at CVPR 2021

Microsoft Diversity Award for Doctoral Research, \$6,000

MITACS Accelerate Research Internship, \$30,000

University of Montreal entrance scholarship, \$37,000

IIIT Hyderabad merit scholarship for summer school, \$1,000

May 2021

Dec 2020

Oct 2020

Jul 2017

Vikram Voleti Page 1 of 3

SERVICE Organizer — ICCV 2021 - Differentiable 3D Vision and Graphics workshop Feb-Oct 2021 OWCV 2021 (Canadian Computer Vision workshop), Canada Feb-Apr 2021 GRAPHQUON 2020 (Canadian Computer Graphics workshop), Canada Oct-Dec 2020 Reviewer — Journal on Computer Vision and Image Understanding, CVPR 2022, ACML 2021, NeurIPS 2021, ICCV 2021, CVPR 2021 (Outstanding Reviewer), ICLR 2020, NeurIPS 2020, ICML 2020, NeurIPS 2019, CCAI @ ICLR 2020, CCAI @ NeurIPS 2019, LLD @ ICLR 2019 C/C++, CUDA, HTML/CSS, Javascript, Jax, Keras, LATEX, MATLAB, OpenCV, OS X, Python, PyTorch, R, SKILLS Shell, SLURM, Tensorflow, Ubuntu, Verilog, Windows Deep learning, computer vision, machine learning, research and development, generative modeling, NeRF, score-based diffusion models, normalizing flows, Neural ODEs, GANs, Transformers, large-scale training, image generation, video prediction, 3D pose estimation, 3D rendering, text-to-image, text-to-3D, text-to-4D Talks • "Diffusion models for solving video tasks" — INRIA, France [slides] Feb 2023 • "MCVD: Masked Conditional Video Diffusion" — NeurIPS 2022, New Orleans, USA [slides] Dec 2022 • "SMPL-IK: Learned Morphology-Aware Inverse Kinematics for AI Driven Artistic Workflows" Dec 2022 — SIGGRAPH Asia, Diagu, South Korea [slides, video] • "Normalizing flows" — Learning Representations (course), University of Montreal, Canada Nov 2022 • "Score-based Denoising Diffusion Models - a tutorial" — Mila, Canada [slides, video] Sep 2022 • "Solving Video Tasks using Denoising Diffusion Models" — Samsung Toronto, Canada [slides] Aug 2022 • "MCVD: Masked Conditional Video Diffusion" — Mila, Canada May 2022 • "Denoising Diffusion GANs" — Mila, Canada [slides] Feb 2022 • "Training GANs by Solving ODEs" — Mila, Canada [slides] Apr 2021 • "Score-based Generative Models with SDEs" — Mila, Canada [slides] Feb 2021 • "Continuous Normalizing Flows" — Mila, Canada [slides] Sep 2020 • "GANs: the story so far" — Summer Symposium on AI Research, India [slides, video] Jul 2020 • "A brief tutorial on Neural ODEs" — Mila, Canada [slides, video] Jul 2020 • "Mathematics of Neural ODEs" — University of Guelph, Canada [slides] Apr 2020 • "Simple Video Generation using Neural ODEs" — IIIT Hyderabad, India [slides] Jan 2020 • Tutorial on "GANs" — AI for Social Good Summer Lab, Montreal May 2019 • "BigGAN" — Mila, University of Montreal, Canada [slides] Oct 2018 • "Image de-fencing using RGB-D data" — MPI Informatics, Saarbrücken, Germany [slides] Feb 2018 • "Intuition behind LSTMs" — IIIT Hyderabad, India [slides] Feb 2018 • Tutorial on "Back-propagation" — IIIT-Hyderabad, India [slides] Aug 2017 • "Mathematics of back-propagation" — GreyOrange Robotics, India [slides] Feb 2017 Past KU Leuven, Belgium — Supervisor: Prof. Ingrid Verbauwhede, ESAT Summer 2013 Internships • Designed arithmetic operations using Carry-Free Logic, simulated circuits in Xilinx IIT Kharagpur, India — Supervisor: Prof. Aurobinda Routray, Electrical Engineering Summer 2012 • Made a gesture recognition program in MATLAB using Hidden Markov Models Imperial College, UK — Supervisor: Prof. Peter Cheung, Electrical & Electronics Summer 2011 • Measured the relative power consumption among the LookUp Tables (LUTs) of an FPGA Thesis Supervisor: Prof. Rajiv Sahay, Electrical Engineering, IIT Kharagpur, India Projects Master's thesis — "De-fencing of Images using RGB-D Data" 2013 - 2014 • Elimination of fence-like occlusions, and inpainting of images using RGB-D data • Nominated for Best Project Award among three departments, research work published at ICAPR 2015

Vikram Voleti Page 2 of 3

• Measurement of synchronization between audio and video using bilabial cues in both modes

2012 - 2013

Bachelor's thesis — "Identification of Bilabial Lip Closures in Audio and Video"

RESEARCH
PAPERS
(SELECT)

3

- [1] NeurIPS 2022 "MCVD: Masked Conditional Video Diffusion for Prediction, Generation, and Interpolation", V. Voleti, A. Jolicoeur-Martineau, C. Pal [arXiv]
- [2] NeurIPS 2022 Workshop "Score-based Denoising Diffusion with Non-Isotropic Gaussian Noise Models", V. Voleti, C. Pal, A. Oberman [arXiv]
- [3] SIGGRAPH Asia 2022 "SMPL-IK: Learned Morphology-Aware Inverse Kinematics for AI-Driven Artistic Workflows", V. Voleti, B. N. Oreshkin, F. Bocquelet, F. G. Harvey, L. Ménard, C. Pal [arXiv]
- [4] Submitted to a journal "Multi-Resolution Continuous Normalizing Flows", V. Voleti, C. Finlay, A. Oberman, C. Pal [arXiv]
- [5] ICLR 2022 "FairCal: Fairness Calibration for Face Verification", T. Salvador, S. Cairns, V. Voleti, N. Marshall, A. Oberman [arXiv]
- [6] CVIS 2022 (Oral) "Plankton-FL: Exploration of Federated Learning for Privacy-Preserving Training of Deep Neural Networks for Phytoplankton Classification", D. Zhang, V. Voleti, A. Wong, J. Deglint
- [7] Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence (journal) "Generative Models of Brain Dynamics", M. Ramezanian-Panahi, G. Abrevaya, JC. Gagnon-Audet, V. Voleti, I. Rish, G. Dumas [arXiv]
- [8] FSS at AAAI 2022 "Towards Generating Large Synthetic Phytoplankton Datasets for Efficient Monitoring of Harmful Algal Blooms", N. Bamra, V. Voleti, A. Wong, J. Deglint [arXiv]
- [9] ICML 2021 Workshop "Improving Continuous Normalizing Flows using a Multi-Resolution Framework",
   V. Voleti, C. Finlay, A. Oberman, C. Pal
- [10] ICLR 2021 "gradSim: Differentiable simulation for system identification and visuomotor control", K. M. Jatavallabhula, M. Macklin, F. Golemo, V. Voleti, L. Petrini, M. Weiss, B. Considine, J. Parent-Lévesque, K. Xie, K. Erleben, L. Paull, F. Shkurti, D. Nowrouzezahrai, S. Fidler [arXiv]
- [11] MLSys 2021 "Accounting for Variance in Machine Learning Benchmarks", X. Bouthillier, P. Delaunay, M. Bronzi, A. Trofimov, B. Nichyporuk, J. Szeto, N. Sepah, E. Raff, K. Madan, V. Voleti, S. E. Kahou, V. Michalski, D. Serdyuk, T. Arbel, C. Pal, G. Varoquaux, P. Vincent [arXiv]
- [12] ICML 2020 "Learning to Combine Top-Down and Bottom-Up Signals in RNNs with Attention over Modules", S. Mittal, A. Lamb, A. Goyal, V. Voleti, M. Shanahan, G. Lajoie, M. Mozer, Y. Bengio [arXiv]
- [13] NeurIPS 2019 Workshop "Simple Video Generation using Neural ODEs", V. Voleti, D. Kanaa, S. E. Kahou, C. Pal [arXiv]
- [14] ICML 2019 Workshop "Comparing Normalization in Conditional Computation Tasks", V. Michalski, V. Voleti, S. E. Kahou, A. Oritz, P. Vincent, C. Pal, D. Precup [arXiv]
- [15] ICASSP 2019 "Cross-Language Speech Dependent Lip-Synchronization", V. Voleti, A. Jha, V. P. Namboodiri, C. V. Jawahar [pdf]
- [16] CVPR 2018 Workshop "Lip-Synchronization for Dubbed Instructional Videos", V. Voleti, A. Jha, V. P. Namboodiri, C. V. Jawahar (FIVER) [pdf]
- [17] ICAPR 2015 "A Multimodal Approach for Image De-fencing and Depth Inpainting", S. Jonna, V. Voleti,
   R. R. Sahay, and M. S. Kankanhalli [pdf, IEEE]

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Montreal, Montreal, Canada — Guest Lecturer

Nov~2020

 $\bullet\,$  Representation Learning (IFT 6135) by Prof. Aishwarya Agrawal

University of Montreal, Montreal, Canada — Teaching Assistant

Sep-Dec 2020

• Fundamentals of Machine Learning (IFT 6390) by Prof. Ioannis Mitliagkas

Summer Symposium on AI Research, India — Guest Speaker

Jul~2020

 ${\bf University\ of\ Montreal},\ {\bf Montreal},\ {\bf Canada-Teaching\ Assistant}$ 

Sep 2019

• Fundamentals of Machine Learning (IFT 6390) by Prof. Ioannis Mitliagkas

IVADO/Mila Deep Learning School, Montreal, Canada — Teaching Assistant

Sep 2019

AI for Social Good Summer Lab, Montreal, Canada — Lecturer

May 2019

TalentSprint, Hyderabad, India — Mentor, Foundations of AI & ML (inaugural program) — Jan-May 2018

• Designed and presented tutorials on machine learning, and mentored industry professionals

Vikram Voleti Page 3 of 3